Nicole: Let’s have a look at the
different ways that data can be stored.
Abraham: External Hard drives can be
used to store copies of important files.
The benefit for this is that they
are portable and sturdy and extend
the storage capacity of a computer.
They should always be encrypted
especially when sensitive data is stored.
Nicole: Cloud storage is becoming
more popular for safe storage of
files and can be accessible from any
device which has secured access to it.
We all use cloud storage everyday as
many emails are stored in the cloud.
Cloud storage means data is kept separate
from a user’s location and can be
available 24/7 allowing organisations
extra storage and web services without
investing in expensive hardware up front.
It’s important to ensure that any cloud
storage has the right access controls
because it’s so highly available
over the internet that only the right
people have permission to access it.
Abraham: Flash drives are useful to keep
data to hand, but they are easy to lose.
Flash Drives should always be
encrypted, and password protected,
especially when storing sensitive data.
Nicole: Back ups are copies of
the system or network data for
file restoration or archiving.
They are an essential part of a
‘business continuity’ plan for
data protection and recovery.
Business critical data should always
be backed up regularly along with other
key software components of a system.
This not only stops opportunities
for blackmail by ransomware, it also
protects from the impact of fire,
flood or physical damage or theft.
Data backups should not be accessible
to staff or permanently connected to
the same network as the original over
a LAN to stop them being infected by
Ransomware and other malware, should
that network become compromised.
You wouldn’t want a breach to
take out both the live data
and your backups as well.
It’s also important to remember
to ensure that your backups have
the same or more stringent access
controls on as the live data.
Abraham: Passwords are strings of
characters that verify the identity of
users during the authentication process.
Some people use the same password
all the time, which is not good!
This means that if one password is found
out, criminals will subsequently know
the passwords to all your accounts.
Some have too many and can't
remember them all so write them down!
Also, not good.
Passwords need to be changed regularly
and should include different characters
such as numbers, caps and lower-case
letters and other characters.
Password managers are a good way of
ensuring that you can have complex
and unique passwords for every website
without having to remember them all.
The longer the password is the
better as it is harder to crack.
Passwords can be made more secure
by processes like 'hashing' and
'salting' which puts them through an
algorithm that turns plain text into
an unintelligible series of letters
and numbers so that if a password is
breached, the criminal is unable to
find out what your actual password is.
Nicole: To prevent 'malware' from
affecting a system and to protect
data, antivirus software also known
as anti-malware should be used and
enabled on all computers and systems.
These should always be kept up to
date to cover the latest threats.
Abraham: Operating systems should
also be kept up to date and often
include antivirus software and
firewalls which create a 'buffer
zone' between a network and external
networks such as the internet.
Operating systems should be set
to 'automatically update' and when
updates are no longer available,
operating systems may need to be
changed to a newer, more current OS
or even a brand new computer system.
Nicole: Share level permissions
manage access to folders shared over
a network and don't apply to users
who log on locally, whereas file level
permissions grant access directly to
individuals’ objects such as files,
folders, or hard disks on servers.
Share permissions should be granted on a
role-based access control [RBAC] model.
This means ensuring that people are
granted access to those shared files
depending on what their role is.
For example, only people in the
Finance Department should be
able to access the shared space
containing the finance documents.
Files within a given shared space
should also be further restricted.
For example, within the finance
department, perhaps only the
payroll people should have
access to salary information.
Abraham: Encryption is a type
of cryptography where a message
is encrypted so that only
authorised parties can read it, converting
plain text into an unintelligible
series of letters and numbers.
Encryption is crucial in helping protect
against bad actors from around the world.
If all information was plain text
sensitive materials like passwords
and health records and bank
account information could be stolen
and sold to the highest bidder.
Encryption works by granting a pair of
keys that allows only the holders of
the keys to decrypt and read the data.
It’s therefore incredibly important to
keep control over who has these keys.